A Guide to the Papers of James Southall Wilson 1908-1936
Special Collections Department, University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
Papers of James Southall Wilson, 1908-1936
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
12708-e
This collection consists of ca. 555 items.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
This collection was given to the Library on May 10, 1988, by Staige Blackford of the University of Virginia, Charlottesville, Virginia.
Scope and Content Information
This collection consists of ca. 555 items, 1908-1936, pertaining to James Southall Wilson's involvement in the Bread Loaf School of English in Vermont and the Southern Writers Conference, and his teaching career as a member of the University of Virginia faculty. Included is correspondence, poetry and essays, examinations and grade books for this University, printed material, and miscellaneous related papers.
There are poetry and essays by Wilson, Lawrence Lee, and Nancy Tucker Wilson. Material concerning the Bread Loaf School of English (an extension of Middlebury College) located in Bread Loaf, Vermont, includes correspondence with R. M. Gay, H. G. Owen, Arnold B. Swift, and Theordore Morrison, a brochure (1929), syllabi, lists of students, and copies of "The Crumb." Material relating to the Dictionary of American Biography includes letters from its editor, Dumas Malone, and J. Westmore Willcox, as well as biographical data on Thomas W. White, Sarah Helen Power Whitman, and Louise Collier Willcox.
"Letters to James Southall Wilson" are arranged in chronological order and cover various subjects such as the University of Virginia, editing and publishing, and work on an interpretation of [Henry] James. Correspondents include John Calvin Metcalf (July 10, 1922), William E. Dodd (April 5, 1930), Alfred A. Knopf (April 23, 1932), Elmer Irving Carruthers (November 15, 1934), Harry Hayden Clark (October 5, 1935), Harry Clemons (April 4, 1936), Jay B. Hubbell (May 11, 1936), and Herbert F. Jenkins (May 11, 1936). Also included is a carbon copy of a letter, November 15, 1932, from Wilson to Governor John Garland Pollard on behalf of State Forrester Chapin Jones. Correspondents writing about the Southern Writers Conference include J. Donald Adams, Edwin Anderson Alderman, Albert George Adam Balz, Roark Bradford, Paul Green, Archibald Henderson, DuBose Heyward, John Lloyd Newcomb, Cale Young Rice, and Stark Young. These letters are arranged alphabetically by writer and discuss positive and negative opinions of holding the conferences, planning, and suggestions.
Arrangement
Letters to James Southall Wilson are arranged chronologically; letters concerning the Southern Writers Conference are arranged alphabetically by writer.
Contents List
- Manuscripts
  - "Best Sellers by Candlelight" by James Southall Wilson n.d. (Box 1)
  - "The Changing English Novel" by James Southall Wilson n.d. (Box 1)
  - "The Changing Novel" by James Southall Wilson n.d. (Box 1)
  - "The Town that Jack Built" by James Southall Wilson n.d. (Box 1)
  - Address for Anniversary of the First Peter Quince Book Talk by James Southall Wilson n.d. (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous Manuscripts n.d. (Box 1)
  - Poetry by Lawrence Lee 1932-1935, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Poetry by James Southall Wilson 1908-1919, n.d. (Box 1)
  - Poetry by Nancy Tucker Wilson n.d. (Box 1)
- Topical
  - The Bread Loaf School of English of Middlebury College, Bread Loaf, Vermont 1920-1936 (Box 1)
  - Dictionary of American Biography 1933 (Box 1)
  - Letters to James Southall Wilson 1922-1936
  - Letters to James Southall Wilson re Edgar Allan Poe 1932-1936
  - Miscellaneous Notes n.d. (Box 1)
  - Southern Writers Conference 1931
  - Southern Writers Conference Correspondence 1931-1932
  - University of Virginia Committees 1934, n.d. (Box 1)
  - University of Virginia English Courses Grade Books kept by James Southall Wilson 1919-1932 (Box 2)
  - University of Virginia English Courses taught by James Southall Wilson 1917-1936, 3 folders (Box 2)